All right,
let's talk about loops and we'll look at some code and then
we'll get into the history of the way that like loops have been
used by sound artists and experimental composers for some time.
And then we'll look at how this runs.
So we have what should be familiar here as
kind of a boilerplate opening HTML code,
character encoding settings,
viewport scaling for mobile devices.
This all comes automatically if you save a file as h .html
and just hit the exclamation point at the beginning and tab.
Some style.
We have a background image on the body,
which is a painting by a friend of mine from 2016.
It's called Zux,
a Marge, California,
very talented artist who runs a
shopping L.A.
that does animation and puppets and stuff like that for the studios.
Our HTML and body has have no margin and the body and HTML have a
minimum height of the full screen because I want the background to be.
To take up at least the entire background,
otherwise the content height might limit that.
We have a button.
That's a tag.
I don't think I've used yet in this course,
but buttons are what they sound like.
They're good things to attach click events to.
There are actually some accessibility tags that
I did not apply to this button and I will actually
put those in after the fact as an addendum.
I have a displayed as block because I wanted to be on its own line.
I made the font size really big and I
made the background slightly transparent.
Kind of a slightly transparent version of papaya web actually.
I typed in papaya web and then I changed the alpha level in the
color selector here.
That was all the way at the top.
It would still be papaya web.
We have audio and video tags that I have
set the width for and then put a border on
and then the video tags get a minimum height of 200 pixels.
I have four players here,
two of them audio,
audio,
video, video,
all loading the same MP3. Those of you who know what an MP3 is,
you might be asking,
an MP3 isn't video.
Why did you put an MP3 in a video tag?
The reason is because I'm also using time text
on these elements.
If you put time text in an audio tag,
there isn't actually space
for it to put it in.
Even if you give the
audio element through CSS,
height and width,
it won't show the text
with the element.
You actually have to custom code your own
stuff that operates on the text track
property of the JavaScript element
and then like iterate through the cues.
Basically make something that displays the text as you go.
It's a lot easier to just make a video tag
and have it show the text in the video tag.
You'll see what that looks like.
Basically, if you have audio with captions,
the hack is to put it in video instead of audio.
I have a button that says play all.
I'm setting this variable to contain a query selector
for all the video tags and all the audio tags.
All four of our players should go into this Ida readable,
this array here,
which we can loop through.
Then I add a click event to the button so that when it's clicked,
it does this thing.
What this thing is is it runs through loop of all of the audio tags,
all the video tags.
It sets their current time to zero so they start
at the beginning if they're not the beginning.
Then I'm getting a random number.
Here's the function down here.
It's between 0.009 and negative 0.009.
These are just, I just kind of tweaked.
I just wanted something that was having
poor tolerance on a
cheap real estate.
I just wanted to build a real machine.
For each of the audio,
they get their own arbitrary,
a little bit faster or a little bit
slower than what normal speed would be.
I dumped that number to the console.
I set the playback rate to 1 plus that number.
If it's a negative number,
it will be less than 1. If it's...
I'm going to put this loop runs,
they all play at the same time.
I did have this directive to remove the controls,
but I actually like leaving the controls on because,
as you'll see, you can see the progress bar.
And seeing over time,
the way that the progress bar stop winding up is useful.
So that is all the code here.
I was a little cheap and lazy.
This background image that you'll see in a moment directly from Arge's
website so that I didn't have one more file to add to my repository.
That doesn't always work,
but it did work in this time.
So before we look at that code,
let's talk about tape loops.
So going back to the 60s,
and Steve Reich wasn't the first person to do this,
but he's probably the person who's most known for the practice.
He had made a tape recording of a street preacher.
He had a
union square in San Francisco during the Cold War,
the Cuban Missile Crisis.
This guy's preaching about Black Panthecoastle
preachers preaching about the end of the world.
Reich gets home.
He's listening to the recording.
There's this part where it's like,
it's going to rain.
He's talking about real fire and brimstone stuff.
And he makes a copy of it.
And he has it on these two real to real machines.
And hits play at the same time.
And it starts out.
They're totally in sync.
And it's like this centered in his headphones.
And it's like this really,
a lot of emphasis,
total alignment.
But then they slowly break apart.
Steve Reich is also known for developing the iPhone ringtone.
And so somebody made this to kind of be the equivalent of
the tape loop.
And you can hear this familiar sound
repeating and then falling out of sync.
Similar effect to it's going to rain,
similar effect to come out and show them and some
of other other of Reich's early tape loop pieces,
which I'm also linked to.
Now you can hear the doubling.
So here we go.
We have our four elements.
We have our painting of Mark Zuckerberg and Tila Tequila.
We have a sound file,
which I just took two seconds out of.
Ben Grocers order of magnitude.
And I handmade some subtitles for it,
which I think I think I got what he's saying.
But you'll see them on these bottom two elements.
But not on the top two elements,
because as I said,
audio elements don't get some subtitles.
So I'll let this
run for a couple minutes and just shut up.